Hello and welcome back
to Arya Nagarjuna.
And here we go.
And we're going to go
till 5:25, right Tim?
All right, good.
We had 7 options for causes and effects
that were basically separate.
And then here's option number five.
The result being triggered,
does it have a nature of its own
or is it devoid of such a nature?
So now, notice that they've switched
the meaning of voidness here?
Before, voidness meant is the
cause devoid of the result.
And now we're asking,
is the result devoid
of a nature of its own?
So different devoids.
,'BRAS BU MI STONG SKYE MI 'GYUR,
,MI STONG 'GAG PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
,MI STONG DE NI MI 'GAGS DANG,
,MA SKYES PAR YANG 'GYUR PA YIN,
,'BRAS BU MI STONG SKYE MI 'GYUR,
There cannot be a starting
if the thing is not devoid of a result.
Let me think about this.
I think that first line might be talking
about the old kind of devoid.
Let's go to the commentary.
'BRAS BU SKYE BA RANG BZHIN
GYIS STONG PA'AM MI STONG
GANG ZHIG SKYE GRANG,
By the way, that SKYE GRANG
in the first line is a new
expression. I've never seen it.
But he started to use it over and over
and now it's clear. It means,
"I'll give you a couple
choices, you choose one."
So SKYE GRANG means
I'll give you a couple choices,
you tell me which one you like.
'BRAS BU SKYE BA RANG BZHIN
GYIS STONG PA'AM MI STONG
Oh, that was the line that
was messed up in the carving.
The carving said the same thing
for options four and five.
So one of them had to be
wrong, and it's this one.
And what it really should say
is 'BRAS BU SKYE BA RANG
BZHIN GYIS STONG PA'AM
"Is the growing of the result,
"is the starting of the result,
"is the growing of the result
empty of its own nature or not?"
You tell me what you think.
Now, he's not saying the
cause is empty or not
or the result is empty or not.
He's talking about the
growing of the result,
is it empty or not. Got it? Different.
Is the growing of the result empty or not?
DE LA 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS
YOD PAS MI STONG PA CHOS CAN,
Let's consider a result,
which was not empty of
having its own nature.
Let's take the case of a result,
which was not empty of its own nature.
SKYE BAR MI 'GYUR BAR THAL,
It cannot start because
RTEN 'BREL MA YIN
It's not dependent origination.
It would not exhibit
dependent origination.
So, there he's just,
he's just used it as a
reason in an argument,
but it's a profound principle
that he's talking about.
What is it?
If something were dependent origination,
it could not have its own nature.
Sorry, it would have to be
empty of its own nature.
If something were dependent origination,
it would have to be
empty of its own nature.
DE 'DRA BA'I MI
STONG PA DE NI CHOS CAN
If it were not empty of its own nature,
if it were not empty of its own nature,
it couldn't be dependent origination,
and it couldn't
'GAG PA
Which means what?
It could never stop.
Because RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PA'I PHYIR
that's sort of a cheap argument:
because it has its own nature. Thanks.
By the way, he has repeated
over and over again
that if something had its own nature,
it could never come to a stop,
because then it would lose
its nature. That's all.
It's been a repeated argument
that if something had its
own nature, it couldn't die
because that means its
nature would have to change
and it wouldn't be its own nature anymore.
So things that have their
own self-existent nature
could never stop.
Because then they would be different
from what they were before,
and that's not possible
if a thing has its own nature.
'GAG PAR MI 'GYUR BAR THAL,
RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PA'I PHYIR,
KHYAB STE, RANG BZHIN LA
LDOG PA MED PA'I PHYIR,
Here's the punchline.
If something is something's nature,
its true nature, it cannot be modified.
That nature cannot be modified.
It cannot.
LDOG PA means
to turn it back, stop it.
It could not be changed or stopped,
if it were a true nature.
If it were an inherent
nature, it couldn't be stopped
because then the thing wouldn't
be what it was anymore.
You couldn't cut the cancer out
without killing the patient,
something like that.
All right.
DE BZHIN DU MI STONG PAR 'DOD
NA NI MI 'THAD DE, DE NI
MA 'GAGS PA DANG MA SKYES PAR
YANG 'GYUR BA YIN PA'I PHYIR,
If you deny that the result
could have any nature of its own,
then it could never stop or start.
It would have to have some nature,
but not a self-existent nature.
Not an immutable nature.
'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD
PAS STONG PA NI CHOS CAN,
Let's take the fact that
the result doesn't exist
through any nature of its own.
JI LTAR NGO BO NYID KYIS
SKYE BAR 'GYUR ZHING JI
LTAR NA NGO BO NYID KYIS 'GAG
PAR 'GYUR BAR NI MI 'THAD DE,
If the result were empty
of any nature of its own,
it could never start and never stop.
'THAD DE, RANG BZHIN
GYIS STONG PA'I PHYIR,
Because it wouldn't have
any nature to change.
If it had its own self-existent nature,
it could never stop especially.
If it didn't have any nature at all,
it couldn't start or stop.
So it has a nature, but
not a self-existent nature.
I don't like my picture so
much, I'm going to skip it.
'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS STONG
PAR 'DOD PA DE YANG NGO BO
NYID KYIS MA 'GAGS PA DANG MA
SKYES PAR YANG THAL BAR 'GYUR
BA LA NI KHO BO CAG NI 'DOD
KYANG KHYED DE LTAR MI 'DOD DE
'GAL BA YIN NO,,
Yes, that's okay, we don't need that.
All right, I have some
Sanskrit words for you
just to take a break and have some fun.
I don't know. I have fun with Sanskrit.
Here are some words that you could,
they're going to apply very
heavily to the next section.
Say: ekatva.
- [Students] Ekatva.
- So Sanskrit doesn't have a v,
it's like a wa: ekatva.
There's a @(unknown)
coming from the victory.
If you know Hindi...
Ekatva means one and the
same, one and together.
GCIG TU 'GYUR means cause and effect
have become one and the same.
Cause and effect are one and the same.
Eka means one.
Ek, do, teen, chaar, panch, chhe, sat -
these are Hindi.
So eka means one.
Ekarasa
What's that?
Single song. Yes.
And so 'eka' came into the word ego,
and from aham, you know aham?
And then 'tva' is always -tion or -ness.
So ekatva means sameness or oneness.
It's going to come in handy here.
Are the cause and the
effect one and the same?
And they're not. Right?
They're not ekatva.
Okay, next word.
Anyatva. And it doesn't mean onion.
'Anya' means other, something
other, opposite of 'eka'.
Eka means 'they're one and the same'.
Anya means 'they're something else',
which is an- /i - not go together.
An- /i- 'don't go together'.
So anyatva means
GZHAN DU 'GYUR, something else.
If they're not one,
are they something
different from each other.
Basically from the privative a-,
privative means negative a-,
it's the Greek term for it.
And it's 'don't go together', anyatva,
an-ya-tva.
All right, next word there
and there's a nice one here.
Say svabhāva.
- [Students] Svabhāva.
- Sorry, svabhāvas.
- [Students] Svabhāvas.
- adbhūta.
- [Students] adbhūta.
- Okay, and I'm not sure
that should be a long bhāva,
that's what the dictionary had,
but I'm suspicious a little bit.
- [CK] There's two, bhāva
and bha both mean 'went'.
- This one's to be, no long a.
'Light' is long a, so I'm
suspicious of this one.
But anyway that's a tradition we have.
NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD PA means exist
through some nature of its own.
Svabhava, 'sva' means 'own',
comes from su, like suicide,
to kill, 'cide' means 'kill',
like regicide or homicide.
Human killing, homicide.
And 'sui' means 'yourself'.
So sva means self. Bhava means nature,
like bhū meaning to be.
So, svabhava means its own nature.
Adbhuta is an unusual
word that normally means
'something happened,
but something amazing.'
RMAD DU 'BYUNG BA
in Tibetan, so adbhuta usually means,
like what's the third chapter called?
- [Student] Practice
- What's it called?
- [students speaking indistinctly]
- Vibhuti Padah
Yes, an amazing occurrence, supposedly.
We're going to talk about it.
But the bhuti often means
happen, something happening,
something big.
Bhuti, sometimes it means something big.
So here it means, svabhava
means it got its own nature,
its own nature happened.
NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD PA,
exists through some nature of
its own, not chocolate sauce!
It doesn't need chocolate
sauce for its existence.
It exists as a bowl of ice cream
without the chocolate sauce.
So there are some words
that are going to be
useful in today's class.
All right.
Here's the sixth option
and I think we can
finish the options today,
which is being refreshing somehow.
Result is triggered by a cause,
which is either the same
or separate from it.
Is the result triggered by a cause,
which is either the same as the result
or separate from the result?
And let's look at the possibilities.
,RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU GCIG NYID DU,
,NAM YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
Hey, it would be ridiculous to say
that the cause and the result
were exactly the same thing
because why would one
start from the other.
So, cancel that one.
Second half of the...
and by the way, he repeats
the second and fourth lines,
which is Nagarjuna's style.
That's ridiculous if they're one
and it's ridiculous if they're separate.
He's always saying that.
It's ridiculous if this,
and it's also ridiculous if that.
So NAM YANG 'THAD PA
means totally big boo-boo.
,RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU GZHAN NYID DU,
And here's the guts.
If the cause and the
effect were the same thing,
then what's the point?
If the cause and the effect
are totally disconnected,
then what's the connection?
If they are inherently different,
meaning no point of contact,
then why talk about cause and effect?
,RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU GCIG YIN NA,
If the cause and the result are the same,
,BSKYED BYA SKYED BYED GCIG TU 'GYUR,
then what's being created
and the creator are one and the same.
The creator and the
creation are the same thing.
,RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU GZHAN NYID NA,
If the cause and the effect
are essentially different,
disconnectedly different,
,RGYU DANG RGYU MIN MTSUNGS PAR 'GYUR,
Then things which are appropriate causes
for something to happen and things
which are in no way appropriate causes
for something to happen would both be
the appropriate causes for
something to happen equally.
You could fix the economy by,
I don't know, picking
up a pen or something.
Something that's not a
cause would become a cause,
if they were not connected.
And here's his commentary.
GZHAN YANG RGYUS 'BRAS BU
RANG BZHIN GYIS SKYED NA
If the cause self-existently
causes the result,
GNYIS LAS MI 'DA' BAS
since there would be no essential
difference between them,
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN
GYIS GCIG PA NYID DU NAM YANG
then if the cause and effect
essentially became the same thing,
'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR
that would be wrong. Why?
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN
GYIS GZHAN PA NYID DU YANG NAM
YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,,
Wait a minute.
I'm sorry, I've got to restate that.
GZHAN YANG RGYUS 'BRAS BU
RANG BZHIN GYIS SKYED NA
If the cause causes the
consequence self-existently,
GNYIS LAS MI 'DA' BAS
they could never be other than two things.
They could never be other than two things.
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN
GYIS GCIG PA NYID DU NAM YANG
And that means they could
never be the same thing.
'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR LA, RGYU
DANG 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS
GZHAN PA NYID DU YANG NAM
YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,,
Therefore it's incorrect to say
that they're essentially different.
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU GNYIS RANG
BZHIN GYIS GCIG PA NYID YIN NA
If the cause and the result
are by nature a single thing,
MI 'THAD DE
that's also a boo-boo because
BSKYED BYA 'BRAS BU SOGS DANG
SKYED BYED RGYU LA SOGS THAMS
CAD KYANG GCIG TU 'GYUR
Then all of the things
being created by the cause,
and the cause creating them,
the creation and the creator
would be the same thing.
And I thought this
would be a good picture.
Then the mother would be kissing herself?
If the creator and the
created were the same thing,
then this is a picture
of James Brown's mother,
[students Laughing]
kissing themself.
- [Student] I'm so handsome
that I could kiss myself.
- I'm so handsome I could kiss myself.
All right.
'BREL MED DON GZHAN
By the way, this is a common idiom.
'BREL MED DON GZHAN means
if there's no relationship
between them at all,
and they're just two separate things,
this is a common philosophical expression.
'BREL MED DON GZHAN
LA NI RGYU 'BRAS YIN MIN GYI
DBYE BA MI RUNG BA'I PHYIR
If there was no connection
between the cause and the...
sorry, the creator and the creation,
if there were no connection
between them at all,
then RGYU 'BRAS YIN MIN
then it would be incorrect
to categorize that
as cause and effect.
If there was no relationship
between the cause
and the effect, it would be
incorrect to categorize it
as an example of cause and effect.
Finished the sixth, lets go onto, oh,
did I have a picture? It's coming later.
Number seven, yay, we're almost done!
Result which either does or doesn't exist
through its own nature is
triggered by the cause.
The cause does trigger a result. Yes.
Does it exist through
its own nature or not?
I don't care. Both are wrong.
Let's say it again.
Does the result come from the cause? Yes.
Is it triggered from the cause? Yes.
Is the result which is
triggered by the cause,
does it exist by itself or
not by itself? Both wrong.
So let's look at that one.
,'BRAS BU NGO BO NYID YOD NA,
,RGYUS NI CI ZHIG SKYED PAR BYED,
If the result already existed
through some nature of its own,
then the cause would be unemployed.
If the result already existed
through some nature of its own,
the cause would be unemployed.
What would the cause have to do?
,'BRAS BU NGO BO NYID MED NA,
If the result didn't have
some nature of its own,
,RGYUS NI CI ZHIG SKYED PAR BYED,
then what would be there
for the cause to create?
If the result didn't
have any nature at all,
then what's the cause supposed to do?
Meaning if it didn't exist at all,
because if it doesn't have a nature,
it doesn't have an identity,
it doesn't even have an existence.
Identity theft instead of unemployment.
RGYUS 'BRAS BU SKYED NA
Here's the commentary.
RGYUS 'BRAS BU SKYED NA 'BRAS
BU NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD PA'AM
MED PA
If you say that causes create results,
let me ask you a question.
And we say, "Yes, what's your question?"
When a cause creates a result,
does that result have
its own nature or not?
And both answers you give are wrong.
Why?
DE LA 'BRAS BU NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD NA
If the result existed through
some nature of its own,
then what would the cause have left to do?
NGO BO NYID KYIS GRUB ZIN
SLAR YANG SKYED MI DGOS
PA'I PHYIR,
Once something has a nature of its own,
there's no point to it being caused again.
Once a thing exists with
a nature of its own,
what's the point to causing it over again?
What more can you do?
All right. I found a fruit. You ready?
And the point is, the point,
I have to explain the picture.
These seeds cannot create
this finished pomegranate
because it's already
there. That's the point.
If the finished pomegranate
had any nature of its own,
then what would the seeds have left to do?
Unemployment.
It's too late for them to do anything.
'BRAS BU NGO BO NYID KYIS MED NA
And if the result doesn't
have any nature of its own,
RGYUS NI CI ZHIG SKYED PAR BYED
then how could anything trigger it?
If the result had no identity of its own,
then how could anything
else trigger a thing
with no identity?
KHYED LTAR NA RANG BZHIN GYIS
MED PA DANG MED PA LA KHYAD PAR
MED PA'I PHYIR RO,
Because according to you,
and someone's going to
tell me who is you, ready?
According to you, to lack your own nature
and to be nonexistent at
all is the same thing.
Who would say that?
I'll say it again: not
having your own nature
and not existing at
all are the same thing.
[student speaking Indistinctly]
That's the other guy.
That's the guy who wants
things to be self-existent.
If they're not self-existent,
they don't exist at all. Why?
They don't have any identity.
Then they might as well
be a piece of popcorn
instead of a pomegranate.
They don't have an identity.
So then I chose,
I don't know if this is a good picture,
I was getting desperate.
I was trying to find a case
where the seeds didn't have
anything to do anymore.
I don't know if that works.
If the result had no nature,
then the seeds couldn't make a result
because a result with no nature
wouldn't have any identity at
all. It would be nonexistent.
These seeds are not
going to make a result.
They are not viable anymore.
All right. Someday people will sit down
and look through all my pictures,
and, "This one was good."
Meaning, just kidding.
Now, we say section two.
And there's about a thousand section twos.
And what I have done in the notes,
which you're welcome to have,
I've always identified section
two, which is a lot of work.
So you have to go back
through all the section twos
and find out which one it is.
So I do it in every case
because I want to know
what I'm talking about,
and it takes time.
So here... and unfortunately,
they don't say what's section two,
it's like chapter two
at the head of the page,
and they don't tell
you what's chapter two.
They don't tell you the name
of chapter two, very typical.
That's Tibetan style.
So maybe they want you
to go back any look.
So here, we denied
RGYU NYID RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA DGAG PA
We're going to prove that's it's not true
that the cause taken on its...
the isolated cause,
isolated from the collection
of causes and conditions, etc
and causes and results.
Let's just talk about
cause by itself, unique.
RGYU NYID RANG BZHIN
GYIS YOD PA DGAG PA
We're going to deny that it could have
any nature of its own,
any specific nature of its own.
Just let's isolate causes by themselves.
Let's not talk about them
in context of results.
Here's the root text.
,SKYED PAR BYED BA MA YIN NA,
,RGYU NI 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
If the cause is not triggering anything,
then how can you call it a cause?
,RGYU NI 'THAD PA YOD MIN NA,
If you couldn't call something a cause,
then whose result is it?
Sorry. Which result does it belong to?
I'll say it again.
,SKYED PAR BYED BA MA YIN NA,
If something doesn't
trigger something else,
,RGYU NI 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
you could never call it a cause.
,RGYU NI 'THAD PA YOD MIN NA,
If you couldn't call it a cause,
,'BRAS BU GANG GI YIN PAR 'GYUR,
then whose would the result be?
Who does the result belong
to if there's no cause?
GAL TE RGYU RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PAS
'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD DO ZHE NA,
And this is an interesting argument
and he's been doing this
over and over again.
If the cause has some nature of its own,
then the nature should...
Sorry. If the cause has
some nature of its own,
then the result should have
some nature of its own.
He wants to say that.
The other guy wants to say that.
Look, if the cause has
a nature of its own,
then the result that's connected to it
should have a nature of its own.
If anything has a nature of its own,
anything connected to it should
have a nature of its own.
That's his general position. Why?
MI 'THAD DE, we say MI 'THAD
Why?
RGYUS 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS
SKYED PAR BYED PA MA YIN NA
RGYU NYID KYANG RANG BZHIN
GYIS YOD PA 'THAD PAR
MI 'GYUR LA,
RGYUS 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS
SKYED PAR BYED PA MA YIN NA
If the cause didn't create the result
through any nature of its own,
RGYU NYID KYANG RANG BZHIN
GYIS YOD PA 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR
then he says, if the result has a nature,
the cause must have a
nature. Did I say that right?
Sorry. If the cause has a nature,
then the result should have a nature.
And then we say, "That's
not correct", because
if the cause is not a
creator of the result
through any nature of its own,
then the cause itself could not exist
through any nature of its own.
If the cause didn't create things
through the nature of its own,
then the cause couldn't
have a nature of its own.
RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA
'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR LA,
Picture.
If it didn't start
something from its own side,
it never existed from its own side.
If the cause didn't create
a result from its own side,
then the cause never
existed from its own side.
That's the opposite of
what he wants to say.
He wants to say, if the result
exists from its own side,
then the cause for that result
has to exist from its own side.
We're saying, "No, let's turn it around."
If the cause doesn't
exist from its own side,
then the result doesn't exist
from its own side either.
We kind of agree with his methodology.
RGYU NYID RANG BZHIN GYIS
YOD PA 'THAD PA MA YIN NA
If it's incorrect to say
that the cause itself
existed through any nature of its own,
'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS
YOD PA DE RGYU GANG GI
YIN PAR 'GYUR
then if the cause...
if it's not correct to say the cause
has a nature of its own,
then if a result showed up,
whose is it?
Sorry. If you can't say that the cause
has any nature of its own,
then what result that
has a nature of its own
came from where, please?
I'll say it again.
If the cause doesn't
have a nature of its own,
then where did the
self-existing result come from?
Got it?
If the cause doesn't
have a nature of its own
and you have a result which
does have a nature of its own,
then where did that result come from?
Because you don't have a
cause which matches it.
RGYU GANG GI YIN PAR
'GYUR BA YANG MI 'THAD
What cause does the result
which does have a nature
of its own belong to?
If the cause can't have a
nature of its own on its own,
we said in isolation,
then if you get a result
that does have a nature of its own,
where did it come from?
Because a result that
has a nature of its own
should logically come from a cause
that has a nature of its own.
But if you isolated the cause earlier,
and said it didn't have
a nature of its own,
then you got all those results
that do have a nature of its own.
They don't belong to anybody.
They just popped out
without a cause. Got it?
'BRAS BU GANG YIN PA DE 'BRAS
BU DE SKYED PA'I RGYU DE'I
YIN PAR 'DOD DGOS PA'I PHYIR,
Because you have to say that every result
has a corresponding cause, no?
So if you got a result hanging out there
that did come from itself,
has its own nature,
you got to find a cause that
does have its own nature
to match it with.
But you just said the causes
don't have their own nature in isolation.
Take a cause by itself, it
doesn't have its own nature.
Alright, yes, we're on section three.
TSOGS PA LAS SKYE BA 'GOG
PA'I RIGS PA GZHAN BSTAN PA'O,,
And don't forget this outline
is imposed on the book by Choney Lama.
He has made up the outline
to fit the evidence.
He's like a detective.
He's creating a murder
scene from the blood spots.
So he's imposing a structure on the text,
which is extremely helpful.
And so far, I'd say I vote for it 100%.
I've seen books where the
author pushed it too far
to get their outline in, but
this one seems to work to me.
So the third part here is:
TSOGS PA LAS SKYE BA 'GOG
PA'I RIGS PA GZHAN BSTAN PA'O,,
I'll give you more reasons
why a result doesn't come about
through the coming together
of causes and conditions.
I'll give you another reason
why results don't pop out of circumstances
where you have causes and
conditions coming together,
because that's the one
that we most want to be.
That's the one that feels
most comfortable to us.
Look, Geshe-la,
the seed is there, the water is there,
and the sunlight is there,
and the gardener is there,
fertilize it, then it's going to come out.
The tree is going to come out.
In fact, we had huge
debates in the monastery
of whether it was even possible
to reverse it at that point.
In the millisecond before
the result comes out,
is it possible to cancel
a result coming out
if all the conditions are present?
And the famous answer is,
"Yes." And we're like, "Why?"
And he says, "If a crow flies
down and picks up the seed?"
[laughing]
And you're all like...
[students laughing]
You, guys, can think about that one.
It's supposedly an ancient valid argument.
I think then you'd say the causes
and the conditions weren't there.
Because the condition of the seed
sitting in the dirt wasn't there anymore.
I would say, but it's a famous,
I don't know, the abbot was
just like...[scratches head]
I remember the debate.
TSOGS PA LAS SKYE BA 'GOG
PA'I RIGS PA GZHAN BSTAN PA'O,,
Let's talk about other reasons
why results don't pop out
of, what did we call it?
I'll give you five dollars.
The consummate
convening.
That's my word.
I'm going to use it as
the name of my next band.
The Consummate Convening.
Anyway, try to struggle to imagine
all the necessary causes and conditions
have already come together.
The sugar's there. The flour's
there. The milk's there.
The oven's on. The time
passed. the cake is made.
So we're going to have
a few final arguments
about why we don't like that.
,RGYU RNAMS DANG NI RKYEN DAG GI,
,TSOGS PA GANG YIN DE YIS NI,
,BDAG GIS BDAG NYID MI SKYED NA,
,'BRAS BU JI LTAR SKYED PAR BYED,
If you assembled all the necessary causes
and conditions, and it
couldn't produce itself,
if the causes and the conditions, if the
water, the sunlight, the seed,
the gardener, and the fertilizer
couldn't create the water,
the sunlight, the gardener.
If all the causes couldn't
create themselves,
'BRAS BU JI LTAR
then how could they cause something else?
We need a commentary,
right? I'll say it again.
If the seed, water,
fertilizer, gardener, sunlight
didn't create the seed,
water, gardener, sunlight,
then how could they all
together create a tree?
We need a commentary. Here we go.
,DE PHYIR TSOGS LAS BYAS BA MIN,
Therefore, the result is not created
by the convening of the
causes and conditions.
,TSOGS MIN BYAS PA'I 'BRAS BU'ANG MED,
And if you never had the causes
and the conditions together,
that wouldn't create the result either.
,'BRAS BU YOD PA MA YIN NA,
If there's no result,
,RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA GA LA YOD,
then how can you say all
the conditions collected?
That's that retroactive,
you get to be a cause
because now you produced a result. Got it?
All right, here we go.
[clapping]
RGYUS RKYEN TSOGS NAS
'BRAS BU SKYED DO ZHE NA,
And this is very
reasonable, somebody says,
"Look, you want a result,
just put together all the
causes and conditions,
and the result will pop out.
That's the way it works."
Then we say,
RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA BDAG
GIS BDAG NYID NI MI SKYED DE,
But don't you agree
that the coming together
of the conditions and causes
have not created the
conditions and causes?
Yes, that's okay. We can agree.
Fertilizer didn't give
birth to the fertilizer.
'BRAS BU SKYE BA DON MED
PA DANG RANG LA BYED PA
'GAL BA DANG TSOGS PA RDZAS
SU MED PA'I PHYIR RO,,
Three reasons here, and
one of them is interesting.
Personally.
Here we go.
RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA
When the causes and
conditions come together,
BDAG GIS BDAG NYID NI MI SKYED DE,
they don't themselves create themselves.
Why?
'BRAS BU SKYE BA DON MED PA
If the causes and conditions
could come together
and create the causes and conditions,
then there would be no need for them
to create something else, like a result.
MED PA DANG
That's kind of weird.
Second reason.
RANG LA BYED PA 'GAL BA
It's a contradiction to say
that something created itself.
That's okay.
We can't say the seed created the seed
or something like that,
unless you're talking
about the continuing of the seed itself.
But I like the last one, and
I want to talk about that.
TSOGS PA RDZAS SU MED PA'I PHYIR
And this word RDZAS in Tibetan,
'dravya' in Sanskrit.
Substance, substance.
It's a highly debated
word in all the schools.
So RDZAS means stuff.
He says,
"Conventions of causes and conditions
are not RDZAS."
So they can't create other thing.
They're not substantial
enough to create something.
Not the causes and conditions separately,
and not the causes and
conditions together,
but the convening doesn't make the result.
The convening is just the situation,
it's not a stuff.
The coming together, the
act of coming together
is not stuff, and since it's not stuff,
it doesn't produce anything.
So I don't want to say the coming together
of the causes and
conditions created the tree.
I don't want to say that. Why?
Coming together is just
kind of like an idea.
It's not the actual things.
It's their being in the
same area at the same time.
That's not big enough to make a tree.
Causes and conditions
being in the same area
at the same time is not solid enough
to create a two ton tree.
It's just a condition.
I like that one. It's kind of interesting.
TSOGS PA RDZAS SU MED PAS
RANG GIS BDAG NYID MI SKYED NA
Since the coming together
of causes and conditions
is not like a solid thing of its own,
not like chemicals and nutrients,
MED PAS BDAG NYID MI SKYED NA
if that means it can't produce something,
DES JI LTAR NA 'BRAS BU RANG
BZHIN GYIS SKYED PAR BYED DE,
If the coming together is
not a solid enough thing
to create the result,
then how could it ever create
a result by itself?
It would be like
MO GSHAM GYI BU
300 dollars
MO GSHAM GYI BU.
MO GSHAM GYI BU
It's an idiom.
It means the child of a barren woman.
Famous expression. I don't know.
A child of a woman who lost
her ovaries or something.
That's just not possible,
not a possibility.
What's not possible?
If the coming together
itself is not concrete enough
to produce a result,
then how can you guys be saying
that the convening
self-existently creates a result?
If the coming together,
not the chemicals, not the
seeds, not the fertilizer,
not the warmth of the sun,
but the action of coming together,
If that's not enough of stuff or of things
to create a result,
then why are you talking
about some kind of
self-existent creating a result,
if it's not even a normal
creating of result.
Got it?
Because their original
argument in this section
was the coming together
of causes and conditions
creates the result.
We say, "No."
Would we say the causes and
conditions create the result?
Yes.
[coughing]
Would we say the coming together
of the causes and conditions
creates the result?
No, that's too theoretical.
Would we say the coming together
of the causes and conditions
creates the result
if the coming together itself
exists through some nature of its own?
We say, "That's something
you made up anyway."
[laughing]
All right.
I took a picture. I was trying to...
Now look, you got to realize
what I was trying to do.
I was trying to create a
picture of multiple elements
that didn't have a common purpose.
And it was just a crowd
walking down the street.
They're not walking to build
a snowman or something.
They're just walking down
the street in New York.
They don't have a goal in mind.
The walking of people down the street
doesn't create a snowman.
The people do, if they choose
to go to Lincoln Center,
I think, Lincoln Center Ice Rink.
But if they don't, then
they're just a bunch of people
walking by 5th Avenue up
near John's favorite place.
What was that place called?
No, on the park, the department store?
[students speaking indistinctly]
- [Students] Bergdorf's?
- Bergdorf, yes, yes, yes.
Okay, we're not going to talk about it.
I'm being discreet.
DE'I PHYIR RGYU RKYEN GYI
TSOGS PA LAS BYAS PA'I 'BRAS BU
NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD PA MA YIN NO,,
We have some time, right?
What time we got to stop?
- [Tim] In five minutes.
- Okay, five minutes, we've got just time.
What've we got here?
RANG LUGS
He's finally, not Nagarjuna,
but Choney Lama's going to
say, "Well, what do we think?
I'll tell you what we think."
Yay! You should stand up more often
and tell us about what you think.
[laughing]
Oh, here's.
RGYU RKYEN TSOGS PA LAS 'BRAS BU SKYE YANG
We, in our system, we do agree
that when the causes and
conditions come together,
they do produce a result.
We can say that in Madhyamika,
we can say that. That's okay.
KYANG,
but
TSOGS PA BRDZUN PAS
But the idea, but the
concept of the collection
or the convening is artificial.
Because it's BRDZUN
BRDZUN means a lie.
But what he means is 'artificial'.
The coming together of causes
and conditions is artificial.
It's an artificial concept.
The causes may be solid.
The conditions may be solid.
But the coming together
is sort of like an opinion
or something.
BRDZUN PAS 'BRAS BU YANG
BRDZUN PA SKYED PAR BYED PA
Now, if you want to say
it this way, I'll buy it.
Who's that? Who's I?
Choney Lama.
If you want to say it
this way, I'll buy it.
An artificial convention of people
could create an artificial
result. That's okay.
I'll buy that.
An artificial coming together,
chocolate coated coming together,
if it created an artificial
result of a tree,
that's chocolate coated,
and the whole thing was
chocolate coated, I'll buy it.
Got it?
Then I'm okay with it.
If you mean artificial
trees, artificial causes,
artificial coming together
creates an artificial tree,
I'm okay with it.
Hey, what do you mean by artificial?
I mean it's coming from
me. It's not real out there.
It didn't exist before I
was there. I created it.
Cool.
He's got one more sentence,
It's okay? We got time.
RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA
MIN PAS BYAS PA'I 'BRAS
BU'ANG MED DE,
By the way, I'm not saying
you could ever have a result
if the causes and the
conditions didn't get together.
I didn't say that. That's
not what I'm saying.
DE NI SHIN TU YANG 'GAL BA'I PHYIR,
You guys know
SHIN TU.
That's total crap.
It's like, your stuff is regular crap,
but to say they don't create anything,
now that's total crap.
He's like really funny.
SHIN TU is completely BS.
Your usual stuff about
self-existence is pretty lame.
But if you want me to say that I'm saying
that they don't produce a
result when they come together,
that's ridiculous. I never said that.
One more line.
Oh, by the way, and then
we finish the chapter. Yay!
And then we've got one more
chapter to go for this course,
which is going to be 22
if I'm not mistaken, 21.
Okay, here we go.
JI SKAD BSHAD PA'I RIGS PAS
RNAM PAR DPYAD PA NA 'BRAS BU
RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA MA YIN
NA RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA
RANG BZHIN GYIS GA LA YOD,
If you follow the arguments
I've been making in this chapter
and if we can say that
the result that comes out
is not something that could
exist in and of itself,
then you'd have to logically believe
that the coming together of
the causes and conditions
was also not something
that existed by itself.
That's all I'm trying to say.
I'm trying to point out to you guys
that if the result is not something
that could exist by itself,
then the coming together
of causes and conditions
that created that result, logically,
would have to be the same.
They could not be coming
from their own side.
They must be coming from you.
The fertilizer is coming from you.
The water is coming from you.
The fact that the gardener showed up
is coming from you.
The fact that the sun shone
today is coming from you,
if the tree is coming from you.
Got it?
It's kind of cute.
GA LA YOD, RGYU 'BRAS GNYIS RANG
BZHIN GYIS YOD MED MTSUNGS PA'I
Because it should all be the same.
Whatever's true of the collection
should be true of the tree.
Whatever's true of the tree
should be true of the coming together.
Yay! Onto chapter 21,
which is called
'An Investigation of How Things
Occur and Then Pass Away.'
An Investigation of How Things
Occur and Then Pass Away.
So that's a new topic.
Yay! See you tomorrow.
Hold onto your hats.
Fasten your seatbelt.